welcome Ecom Logistics Nation thank you
for joining today's episode we're on a
mission to share e-commerce Logistics
insights Trends successes and challenges
from the leaders and innovators in our
space
[Music]
Amazon's move to this new Regional
fulfillment model so they've brought low
weeks of cover in from Brands because
they're rebuilding their whole inventory
balancing behind the scenes of their
Network so that they can create micro
fulfillment centers and go point to
point
welcome Ecom Logistics Nation this
episode nanad and I welcome Corey
appearion CEO of DaVinci micro
fulfillment Corey has over 15 years of
experience growing Brands and creating
strategic Supply Chain Solutions he
launched DaVinci micro fulfillment in
May of 2020 and we look forward to this
conversation where we'll break down all
things related to a successful micro
fulfillment program Corey absolute
pleasure to have you join us today and
welcome to the show thanks for having me
the pleasure is all mine this is a big
big milestone for Da Vinci and myself to
be on on this podcast which I feel like
a lot of people say when they come on
here now it's also the other way around
Corey because I just have to add
that you know I've had many
conversations with you in the past the
amount of things that I've learned with
you and then I go out and talk to people
about how much knowledge I have but that
all starts with you specifically in the
Amazon Arena right and we'll get into
that but there is a lot that we are
going to be learning over here today I'm
I'm really looking forward to it that's
awesome yeah absolutely and and after we
get through Corey's Journey we're
actually going to have him take us to
Amazon school so stay tuned for that
here in a few minutes but uh Corey
wanted to start with a little bit about
your journey you have a really
interesting background and it includes
everything from e-commerce merchandising
driving revenue for Brands supply chain
leadership supply chain Consulting and
certainly entrepreneurship with the
launch of Da Vinci and wanted to see if
you could share with the audience kind
of your journey and you know leading up
to that aha moment or decision point you
had uh where you made the decision to
launch DaVinci micro fulfillment yeah
absolutely
um I majored in Supply Chain management
at Syracuse University 2000 to 2004
um at that point in time there were only
four schools in the U.S that offered
supply chain as a major my first week of
college I went to go pick my major I
knew I didn't want to be a finance major
didn't know what I wanted to do and just
literally fell in love with supply chain
right out at the gate point of origin to
point of consumption everything in
between amazon.com was my case study for
four years that was offered that was the
really early days and my junior year uh
to get internship credits I worked in a
Wholesale Distributor that was shipping
Clorox uh Brita water filter
specifically into Amazon's FC Network at
that point in time they had four maybe
five
fulfillment centers and most of it was
shipping into the Lexington Kentucky
area uh and I cut my teeth in the
warehouse and started in the receiving
department and learning inventory and
receiving and everything around the
pickpack and ship operations of bulk
fulfillments and Senior year uh the CEO
of that company who is a Wholesale
Distributor in home and garden Personal
Care electrics Outdoor Living consumer
electronics every major brand of
housewares that you could think of from
Bissell Floor Care KitchenAid Philips
Norelco Etc uh was basically approached
by Amazon Senior Team saying we're
starting this thing called the Dropship
program we're picking you know three
Distributors around the country to start
for these categories we want you to be a
part of it that CEO saw that I added
some 21st century principles of supply
chain and you know called me up a week
before I graduated and said hey we just
got asked to go start this thing called
Dropship we have no idea what it is you
want to you want to come start so I
called one of my professors and said I'm
going to start for this wholesaler can
you come down and walk the floor with me
and give me some pointers he spent a day
with me after he left I Googled how to
wire a CAT5 cable and bought some Reams
and some extra rollers and I pieced
together this Pick and Pack operation
and within two months we launched a
multi-million dollar business and Amazon
gave us uh me specifically an award for
being their top fulfillment partner out
of the out of the categories that they
they had and uh I remember the award uh
like it was yesterday it was uh fastest
response time and and highest attention
to detail out of any vendor there and
you know I can't say that I'm smarter
than anybody else but I've paid
attention and I've learned and I got my
real MBA and experience uh through the
past 20 years of the e-commerce
ecosystem and fast forward I took that
business model and copied it to every
major retailer and I really helped
Brands build their online strategies
through a wholesaler uh through Macy's
and Walgreens and Lowe's and Target and
Walmart and so on so forth really
watched the evolution of 1p 3p
Marketplace in b2c which will break up
art in a little bit and I was not only
building the Pick and Pack operations
and overseeing all the Integrations and
learning all the ins and outs there but
I was also building all the new item
setups and creating all the content and
pulling all the marketing lovers that
were available and I understood very
early on that brands are the ones who
are really asked to do the heavy lifting
they are not set up for each's
fulfillment or single piece returns in
fact back then they were terrified of
that so they would Outsource to a
wholesaler so that they could just get
it off their their p l and the unit of
measure conversions kind of became
someone else's problem in the cash
collection and all of that right the
inventory control and at the same time
it was a one-to-many thing right a
wholesaler like myself at the time could
go integrate with Walgreens and Walmart
and Target and Amazon and just buy from
KitchenAid and then go sell it to all
those channels and basically the problem
with that is that it kind of became a
race to the bottom for a lot of these
Brands because there were Distributors
and suppliers that were selling these
products unauthorized on an Amazon
Marketplace on an eBay on a Walmart
marketplace they would do really well at
Amazon because of Amazon's growth and
they would bring that business direct
but they would want to still continue to
fulfill for a walmart.com and target.com
but the inventory control was really
challenging because there was not enough
volume to sustain that for inbound
truckloads and full full truckloads fast
forward the consumer buying habit is
changing and you know many many years
ago Amazon Prime expected two days you
know and then other channels were
ships your you know leaves your
Warehouse in 48 hours didn't matter how
much you know uh time it took to go
deliver
now that's obviously not the case at all
90 plus percent of consumers out there
opt in for one day delivery in Amazon
Prime not same day not today but next
day so as I went along On my journey and
started learning all the ins and outs of
the ecosystem watching the consumer
buying habit update I spent time in
China manufacturing my own Brands and
getting those brands from online sales
into every major brick and mortar on the
shelf and really understanding that
Global Supply Chain domestic intra
Logistics and how the ecosystem
cohesively works together from an
inventory control the transportation
merchandising and assortment planning
and an integration perspective
I really allowed myself to amass all
this knowledge right and because I've
touched all those things and pulled all
these levers it really brought me to the
place of creating Da Vinci micro
fulfillment which really was birthed out
of the customer buying habit evolving
the operating expense of a large
Distribution Center in one area of the
country trying to fulfill an order in
same day one day two day from a delivery
perspective and understanding how to
replenish inventories and maintain that
flywheel so that you're always creating
turns and
I after I exited my last company I was
reading Walter isaacson's Leonardo da
Vinci book my now five-year-old who uh
was one and a half at the time his name
is Leo so I knew that I was going to
call my next company Da Vinci uh after I
sold my last one and this concept of
micro fulfillment of using smaller
footprint buildings with forward
deployed inventories as the strategy
just was an aha moment for me all the
buildings that I've operated and built
in the past were a million or several
hundred thousand square feet of space in
one or two maybe three areas of the U.S
and there's a lot of challenges with
that type of complexity and size and
forward deployed inventory focused on
picking and packing and uh just fast
turns of of eaches to me is a more
simpler way to do it and although what
we do is complex on some level I think
we we do it in a very simple way from
our pricing model to the technology
we've deployed to how we onboard
partners and we'd be we have become a
growth engine for brands that are
operating in a multi-channel fulfillment
environment that need to fulfill in the
same day one day two day Cadence and an
agnostic category environment
that makes a lot of sense right so one
thing I I have to say you know I
generally say all good operators should
also be tech savvy and All Tech folks
within the warehousing space should be
very well versed with operations and
spend time there for you to be able to
perform your job to the best of your
ability right what you just brought up
right like that 20-year Journey going
from being a brand being a seller being
a you know starting new programs
building operations merchandising
manufacturing transportation
that's the experience right like and I
would say that that makes you
a bit of a unicorn in this space because
there is a lot of people with the
general understanding but the depth of
understanding of all those subjects and
then you just stick to
this
merchandising side of the universe to
say okay how do I help people leverage
and I specifically speak to Amazon right
how do I help people build an Amazon
strategy because that's
the big uh question that you see in the
market that you know most of the folks
that you talk to they still don't have
Amazon strategy a lot of Brands don't
have it a lot of retailers don't have it
and I think
there is a general lack of
consultative and I'm not talking about
Consulting right like but consultative
information that is available
on what should I do an easy button that
basically says here's how my profile
looks how should I be leveraging Amazon
and that's lacking and I think all of
that exists in your brain so we'd like
to squeeze that out yeah no I I want to
share it uh and I really appreciate that
it it's very true I mean I very much
believe in an Amazon and mentality not
Amazon burst there's a lot of companies
there's you know some competitors or
some other companies that they go out
there and it's Amazon verse how do I
just do d2c and Marketplace and the the
reality is is that Amazon's 50 of the US
volume and the inline and offline
experience that customers have from a
halo effect is that is a real thing and
even if you have your Brands merchandise
the right way on Amazon you're gonna get
that benefit because search and research
and education is one of the main reasons
that customers go shop online and 60
plus 70 plus percent of those customers
go right to Amazon first outside of
Google if not more I think a lot of the
argument around you know that not having
Amazon that we heard before and I think
everyone's perspective is changing quite
a bit at this time but
the argument always stood that hey the
brand experience right like when I sell
through my own channel then I have my
branded box and that's what the customer
is getting versus the brown box that
Amazon's gonna send and my brand just
gets diluted but I guess there are
programs where they don't get diluted is
that correct Corey from an Amazon
standpoint that you could leverage your
own fulfillment
or you know partner with the 3pl and
could do it and maybe you know this
could be a good segue into all the
programs that Amazon allows people to
leverage yeah
um there used to be a lot of strict
rules from Amazon if you're in the 1p
side which they now call Direct
fulfillment so that's their vendor
Central side so Amazon has two sides
they have vendor Central and they have
Seller Central Amazon vendor Central you
could ship bulk into their FC and you're
selling it to them and they're retailing
it to the End customer and doing their
fulfillment direct fulfillment is still
vendor Central you're still wholesaling
it to them but they're paying the
freight to the End customer and it's
coming from either the brand or another
suppliers Warehouse typically it's going
to be a third party logistics company
because the Brand's still the vendor of
record there but it could be from a
distributor as well it just is not under
that same vendor number there's no tie
to that so all the data gets lost and
things like that
um and then there's Seller Central and
there's really four ways to sell one of
them is is not as big it's called Amazon
Local where some Brands can get invited
and they can offer same-day deliveries
very zip code specific opportunities
there and the two core ones are uh FBA
which everybody knows about it's more of
a consignment model it's a transfer
order from a brand or supplier into
Amazon they hold that inventory and they
fulfill as orders come in and they pay
every two weeks against the orders that
came in on that two-week time frame
there's a lot of new restrictions on
that and then there's Merchant fulfilled
which is very similar other than the
fact that it's coming from that supplier
or third-party Logistics company's
fulfillment center to the End customer
that brand is responsible for the
outbound Freight and tax Nexus uh and
reporting of that and then the third one
is called seller fulfilled Prime
which is very similar to Merchant field
and just got turned back on and
announced last week that they're now
accepting new applications where you can
earn a prime badge if you hit metrics
from Amazon for one to two Day
deliveries uh six days a week shipping
very very strict metrics not that
unsimilar to the direct fulfillment
metrics a little bit different but you
can buy Amazon's labels essentially and
get a prime badge if you can maintain
metrics across certain regions on that
one to two day radius around wherever
you're shipping from and if you can do
it with a physical location Network
across the US on Direct fulfillment and
seller fulfilled Prime you can get
access Countrywide with a prime badge
outside of Amazon's environment and the
way that I've always sold to Amazon and
to every major retailer just to be clear
being able if you're a brand you're you
have the control this is an inherent
difference in how we look at it and one
of the reasons we incorporate the
merchandising side
because I think it's really important
for Brands to understand who they're
selling to and what products they're
selling because you can't just sell
every item to every online Channel just
like you can't sell every item to every
brick and mortar store however there is
a cohesive nature of an inline and
offline assortment plan and if you are
selling into Amazon who doesn't have a
much of a brick and mortar footprint
right obviously they have Whole Foods
and Amazon go and things like that but
you need to create agility in your own
model where a you're not shipping 100 of
your inventories into Amazon and behold
into low weeks of cover from them uh you
know getting turned off them holding the
inventory and another one of your
retailers dropping price and you get a
buy box issue where all of a sudden
you're selling something below where you
want to be we're getting a chargeback
there's a lot of things that can go
wrong and there's a profitability and
consumer experience so why you would
want to have some of your items asins
they call that's the Amazon stock
identification number backing up your
core items within Amazon's own FC
Network whether it vendor Central or
Seller Central so understanding how
you're selling is I think the most
important thing and the next thing is
what's the assortment that you're
selling so if you're set up to sell
direct to Consumer direct to FC and in
some cases direct to store and
distribution center you can walk up to
any buyer and consumer theoretically and
and and never get a no right you get to
control your own destiny and if you
understand how the ecosystem works and
then you can now pull your own levers
you're just going to be creating
flywheels and creating inventory turns
and that's the name of the game
that's correct yeah also so you know we
spoke about vendor Central and Seller
Central spoke about two programs within
vendor Central right you have the 1p the
traditional retail send stuff to them
then you got the 1p drop ship which is
Amazon direct is that correct direct
fulfillment direct fulfillment and when
it's Amazon direct fulfillment now you
are doing the shipping is that also so I
would assume everything is prime
eligible at that point but then you need
to maintain metrics right well yeah so
when you start on Direct fulfillment
your first 30 days for a new Warehouse
you do not get a prime Edge you have to
earn it and once you earn it you have to
maintain metrics and and they're they're
they're very strict right you have to
ship on time that those goods not only
have to be manifested on time but they
have to be scanned into the carrier
Network on time they have to be
delivering at the same time that Amazon
told the customer that it's delivering
and they and that has to be accurate
right so there's like really four levels
of metric to maintain what they call a
GD guaranteed delivery status and in
many cases it requires uh up to a six
hour cycle time on orders and in that
case uh is the you know the seller of
record would be Amazon right at the end
of the day still the seller of record
the shipper offers
sold by Amazon on site is what you would
see in the buy box not ships by Amazon
and and fulfilled by yeah
that's correct and so so who pays for
the transportation in that particular
scenario Amazon Amazon pays for the
transportation and and they they could
have multiple carriers coming to your
Warehouse
um or sorts or do they have a choice of
where you set up your warehouses as well
because to be able to be
you know you need optimal shipping
strategy you need to be spread out in
multiple locations there is no way you
can pull off uh Amazon direct
fulfillment from a single location is
that wouldn't be the case you can't you
can do it you're just not going to get a
prime badge and Amazon's likely gonna
they're gonna they're gonna route orders
per Warehouse in that case and it
depends if you have inventory in their
FC Network or not and
again this very much goes back to the
categories that you're servicing and the
assortment that you put out on Amazon I
would use if I if I'm a brand and I have
a high volume with Amazon you can't get
invited to vendor Central today unless
you have certain number of volume so if
you're a brand who's already in Vendor
Central I think the first thing you do
is go get a direct fulfillment account
you know talk to your Vendor Manager you
have to have that and and Amazon's move
to this new Regional fulfillment model
so they've brought low weeks of cover in
from Brands because they're rebuilding
their whole inventory balancing behind
the scenes in their Network so that they
can create micro fulfillment centers and
go point to point basically what they've
designed is you know a DaVinci
microfilament I mean I'm not comparing
myself to them but it's the same concept
of smaller footprint buildings and
point-to-point deliveries on a thesis of
inventory control to enable a lower
operating expense same day delivery is a
byproduct of it it's the lower operating
expense it's the critical piece in the
inventory control that's a critical
that makes a lot of sense that makes a
lot of sense and so now just to move on
to the right side because I I have a
diagram in front of me but moving on to
the right side which would be Seller
Central right
within that I think FBA is well
understood you sell you send stuff to
Amazon Amazon ships it on your behalf
charges you acts as a 3pl but then you
said there is fbm and Amazon Local and
then there is SFP and it seems like
first of all fbm you could technically
consider SFP as just a sub program of
fbm right like so you get fulfilled by
Merchant
then you gotta earn yourself into seller
fulfilled Prime right like you you gotta
just how you explain that for the direct
fulfillment it would be similar would
that be accurate yeah it would be and
depending on how your infrastructure is
set up in a perfect world and you can
manage decentralized inventory from a
physical location Network that can
fulfill
same day orders and deliver within one
to two days across the entire U.S I
think you can make the argument
SFP is the way to go exclusively right
there could be some cases where it's
more profitable to do FBA from a freight
perspective or you know and I think the
p l management becomes really important
right if you're doing fbm you're not
getting a prime badge however you can
also make the argument that there are
certain cases especially with new Amazon
cubic inch requirements of what you're
allowed to put into FBA and the turns
within that you want to focus just like
with with vendor Central bulk your full
palette full truckload inventories
your core items at 80 20 rule you want
to put those into Amazon's Network
they're they're their network is their
Network for a reason right the the
biggest and baddest and the best out
there what they do in many categories
non-oversize items specifically like
high value low weight items you know
laptops hard drives things like that yep
there's nobody better you know and it's
hard to say that you're gonna be more
profitable the other way however there
are certain items a first class mail
type item a first class package type SKU
that's a low value low weight item it
may not make sense to put that into
Amazon's Network and although you may
not get a prime badge for that you know
there's a profitability Cadence of
things that you need to be able to sell
to Amazon and if you can manage I think
you can make the argument in certain
suppliers and channels that they should
have all four
FBA Merchant field SFP and Amazon Local
I know many SFP sellers that do that
today
that that and who pays for the
transportation in this case so there is
a merchant yeah is there a case and and
whose label are you buying are you
buying Amazon's label or are can you use
your own rates with whatever carriers in
SFP you're using Amazon's labels okay
and there is no problem no provision for
being able to use your own labels right
uh I I don't believe so in SFP uh the
new program I'm not 100 certain on that
but it's brand new so I'm not sure if if
that's public yet
um but I can tell you on the other on
Merchant field it's 100 your dime and
you know the traditional parcel carriers
in there however there are some local
carriers now that are getting approved
in merchant field and that's that's a
real that's a really big deal okay and
would that be similar to the Amazon
Local because that's kind of the last
program there you can use anybody for
that you could use doordash or Uber if
you wanted to and would you be able to
explain what Amazon Local is exactly as
a program yeah it's basically being able
to have very zip code level detailed
metrics on same-day deliveries that you
can offer in a very short radius around
wherever you're fulfilling from and you
could use any carrier to get it to an
end consumer
so if you wanted to offer you know think
of maybe like uh
you can think of a like a dash Mark
esque type opportunity or like an Etsy
even type opportunity where you know I I
think Etsy is probably more of the
comparison from a from an item
perspective of what you're looking at
and you can get it to the customer in
whatever experience you need to that
sounds fantastic
this covers for me the the entire gamut
am I missing any programs I've heard of
one called Amazon vendor Flex Fender
Flex is a part of direct fulfillment
what Ben Flex is doing is Amazon's
setting up fulfillment operations in New
York fulfillment center or Distribution
Center as the brand that comes with a
cost obviously they are basically
fencing off their area and they go put
Amazon employees and their technology
and conveyors into a small area within a
large Brands Distribution Center and
they then do their own fulfillment and
Amazon they drag you to where you need
to be you know if they want your product
and and your items they're gonna they're
gonna get you there uh and if you can't
um you know get inventory into their FC
uh and they've seen these types of
things they're going to want to do that
and open up that opportunity so that you
know there's a benefit to them to doing
that in in some cases for the brand you
know I think it's a it's a good entree
into direct fulfillment there's
integration challenges at times there
could be
um security type challenges you know
there's certainly inventory control
things where you're moving stuff across
the line and you're still getting a
purchase order from Amazon uh and
there's a cost to that as well but I
think it's a it's a great program for
some yeah for some yeah yeah that that
some happens to be a small number but
yeah it's a great program for some thank
you very much for all of that yeah that
was that was awesome Corey and exactly
what we uh we wanted I think it'll be
interesting with as you said last week
they kind of reintroduced seller
fulfilled Prime with more details to
follow
but I think it's important for everyone
to kind of take a look at those details
because I know nanod and I and then
maybe you do as well we have a lot of uh
scarred tissue from the 20 teens era
when it first came out where you know
running fulfillment centers you would
pick pack and and and get the shipment
out on time so the metrics you hit the
metrics from uh operational standpoint
but when you didn't use Amazon's label
you used a common carrier label you
actually would get penalized if you know
it was supposed to be delivered in two
days and it was delivered in three or
four as a seller under a seller
fulfilled Prime we saw many many many
Brands kind of lose the badge and lose
the right to participate in the program
because the carrier had an issue even if
it was a weather delay a storm it didn't
matter you know if the experience wasn't
there
and we saw a lot of Brands kind of get
um
get removed from that program so I think
it'll be really important to see if
Amazon's going to allow that or now that
they're you know their carrier network
is as strong as it is today they don't
even allow that as an option
it's interesting I mean we're we're
lucky we're um on the direct fulfillment
side we've been invited into the ATS
program so their carrier networks is
actually picking up from our mfcs now to
go deliver
um their their DSP Network and and Fleet
of trucks in addition to UPS and others
um I think the really interesting thing
there though is to see if they're going
to move that into SFP but I think one of
the things you know and it's a lot of
Legacy suppliers are have built their
operation around sfb and they they've
done it well in the locations where
they're operating from uh I don't know
how many are doing it on full national
scale at this point still uh but what I
will say is that the technology and
precision that's available today just in
a few short years off of those parcel
carriers the UPS even post office on
some level uh you know FedEx
specifically for those labels and
understanding exactly somewhat exactly
of a window of when it's going to be
delivered from the origin point is so
much stronger and I think if managed
correctly with the right technology in
the right physical location Network
people can be really successful in this
new program
well I think that that tees us up for
where we wanted to go next was getting
your thoughts on on kind of the State of
the Union for uh everything last mile
delivery and and localized carriers so
um and your thoughts on maybe and maybe
just cover that too on on how local
carriers have evolved over the past you
know a couple years to support same day
one day and two day and and what you're
seeing on that on that front
yeah it's really interesting I think
similarly to how
um
a lot of suppliers walked out of Amazon
SFP or got kicked out of SFP you know
because they couldn't meet the metrics I
think there's a lot of people out there
that are looking down upon decentralized
inventory uh and specifically micro
fulfillment uh because they look at
rapid grocery right and they see these
15-minute Ultra fast deliveries that
failed and they failed in Manhattan
because of zoning an easement and giving
away shopping carts for a hundred bucks
when it costs 300 and solving a problem
that's you know maybe a little too early
and things like that or you know I I
very much believe in automation but you
know robotic companies going in and just
selling you know an offset of capex
right and that that's not necessarily
what brands need right now who again
back to what we were talking about
earlier you know the heavy lifting is
done by the brands they have the control
and I think what they want is inventory
because this is what the customer wants
they want their orders to be delivered
precisely
sustainably and at the lowest cost of
fulfillment and to enable that you need
to get closer to the customer and I
think local carriers are starting to
develop and understand that and they're
doing a lot of things that are really
unique with middle Mile and circation
and that's something that we've focused
really heavily on because if you can
partner with the local carriers and get
inventory and orders injected into local
hubs and they can add a level of
sortation and whether it's being handed
to a gig or a W-2 or a franchise worker
and all of those models exist today and
we can talk about the positives and
benefits and negatives of all of that uh
to me you know that's a really unique
way to do it because you take a physical
location network of X number of
buildings and it feels like 10 or 12 or
15 with that middle mile injection and
there's such great technology out there
now where you can be able to geofence
that shopping cart for d2c channels and
Marketplace channels where the suppliers
are the ones asked to pay the freight
out and you know in a direct fulfillment
Channel
walmart.com1p target.com 1p you know
they're telling you use UPS use FedEx
use ATS and they're telling you where to
ship from typically now you know that
that is evolved um and you have to be
really precise with that you'll get paid
you'll get negatively dinged from a
chargeback perspective if you ship early
you have to ship on time it could be
early or late there there's like a
specific window they give you because of
how the carrier lanes are are built out
so insert this new category of local
carrier some are same-day deliveries
some are next day delivery some are two
Day deliveries the thing that's really
unique about them is that they're very
Regional based most of them uh and even
if they are gig the ones that are
National like a doordash or an Uber or
shipped or folks like that
um you know and vejo even right that is
a gig worker still uh but how they're
creating the quality of the of the
delivery and how they're showing that
precision and that customer touch I
think that's something that's really
unique right now and and you know not to
disrespect UPS FedEx and post office
because what they have built is just
incredible over the past couple decades
and they're the Pioneers right and maybe
on some level dealing with an
innovator's dilemma
um you know yes they drive down the last
block to go deliver packages but they're
not a Last Mile carrier in the sense of
that word uh you know
this point-to-point delivery and this
quality delivery and the cost of that
delivery I think that's the unlock that
they're trying to bring and I think
they're doing a really good job
disrupting and there's probably about
you know 10 to 12 of them out there that
I that I I've you know partnered with
and watching really closely and um there
they have a lot of really bright people
solving problems for them yeah other
than the the you know Ubers and door
dashes of the world though you look at
most of these companies they are one of
the things that I like about it is they
are very regionally or a specific city
or a couple cities focused right it's
not trying to build out this massive
Network and I've said this in the past I
feel like there's going to be some level
of consolidation because a lot of that
Tech looks very similar across the world
right and there is that opportunity to
then build the middle Mile and now you
have a network in play right like you're
gonna start seeing that happen but but
there is also
you know while we talk about all of this
good Tech you know working in this space
I've realized a lot of the W-2s are uh
you know contractors or smaller mom and
pop operations still operate without a
lot of technology so from a track and
Trace capability standpoint and whatnot
it's still lacking in experience and
when that Tech becomes more democratized
right like as a W-2 you can start
getting
more data or you can start you know in
plugging into the ecosystem let's say I
think we are going to start see seeing
some more magic happen within that space
as well yeah I agree I mean technology
is going to unlock a lot right like
machine learning on routes and
consolidation all of it really though
comes down to density and and I agree
with you on the consolidation side very
very much I think you're going to see a
lot of it I think a lot of the tech is
somewhat similar I think the the folks
that have gone to franchise models I
think that's a really unique thing
um I think the gig worker like I think
depending on who you're talking to you
know it could be a good thing it could
be a bad thing
um they're obviously sharing the same
pool of drivers together so at some
point that will be an issue and and you
know you certainly have a risk of you
know government stepping in and creating
issues you know on that behalf
um I think I think those like uh go both
a Canadian company that's operating in
the US right now who's you know building
out a fleet of electric vehicles and
really focused on sortation I think like
they're a really unique company to watch
they've done a really great job and a
really great company as well
um and you know I I see a lot of these
uh middle Mile and sortation folks you
know better trucks and front door
Collective and vejo and warp and Cloud
sort these are all really well run
executing operating companies and some
of them have great Tech and some of them
just have really great operational
execution skills and at some point I do
think you'll see automation come in
there because when it comes to package
sortation if you can build density
there's equipment that can really help
the crazy stuff that's really easy yeah
from assault automation standpoint in
intra Logistics I would say that's one
of the easiest automation pieces that
you could like throw at but you don't
you still don't see a lot of them doing
it right and and I I think you know
they're young companies and they're
raising capital and all those things
right are happening just like all of us
out there but you know you know it's
it's it's where the future is going I
mean
you could have a dark Warehouse
theoretically just sorting with with
automation easier than you can a Pick
and Pack fulfillment operation in my
opinion absolutely much easier and I
mean if you if you if you can build to
certain Dimensions it's super easy have
you induct and what line sorts to what
when we did that back in you know 2005
right that's old school Tech compared to
some of the stuff that's happening and I
know Corey you're working on a bunch of
Automation and whatnot on your side as
well that's way more complex exactly
I think we we mentioned a couple
companies here Corey and I just want to
make sure we we draw a distinction
because it comes up a lot I know it
comes up a lot for me as I'm having
conversations with Brands and retailers
um the difference between micro
fulfillment and maybe what's coined you
know quick Commerce or fast Commerce or
you know delivery within 20 minutes kind
of like the go puff model and as you're
kind of describing and walking through
micro fulfillment and everything I just
maybe if you could just
maybe it's just as simple as how fast
the delivery takes place but any
distinction you can make between those
two different models I think would be
beneficial yeah I mean I think that you
can
um make an argument that speed and size
of a fulfillment center and speed of
delivery are relative in a micro
fulfillment environment I think gopuff
and dashmart operate micro fulfillment
centers because they're getting closer
to customers now they're operating in a
convenience store model so that customer
wants stuff fast and they're willing to
pay for it and they want that
convenience and it's very targeted in
their real estate and where they're
going uh you know you look at Ultra fast
grocery or a a the back of a grocery
store the back of a Walmart right those
are micro fulfillment centers because
they're close to the consumer they're
close to density and population my
definition of micro fulfillment which I
think some agree with is a miniaturized
fulfillment center in a hyper local area
hyper local could be a 20 minute
delivery if it's a frozen you know Pine
device screen that needs to get there in
20 minutes or the customer chooses that
from a Precision perspective it could be
a one to two day delivery as well
exactly we offer 35 to 50 000 square
foot buildings Amazon their same day
micro fulfillment centers are 75 000
square feet they used to be 125 000
square feet after they returned 35
million square feet of you know hundreds
of thousands of square foot you know
buildings because of that operating
expense so I think it's a relative term
and I I think it's more about
positioning for precision and having the
ability to get closer to customers based
on the demand that exists out there
DaVinci has six buildings today that hit
85 percent nexane 100 today not only
because of like the stage of company we
are but we're solving a one two day
problem because most of the deliveries
out there just like I mentioned earlier
that Amazon's 50 of the demand in the US
for e-commerce most of the deliveries
are serviced by parcel and parcel can't
really do better than next day so you
need to be positioned in a place where
you can hit a next day and two-day
delivery because that's what consumers
want and if given the option between the
same day next day and two day
I I would think that they're mostly
going to choose next day and I think
there's a lot of data that supports that
on the on the general merchandise side
of things for sure right like just on
the on the other side it's not just
given the choice it's also the unit
economics of being able to do some of
that right so and maybe that's another
and it's not a question but just a point
to make over here is micro fulfillment
does not work in a silo right like the
closer you get in a hyper dense
environment the real estate cost goes up
your Cube cost goes up you need a
strategy where you your purchasing
strategy has to align with your storage
strategy or your you know manufacturing
strategy as to align with your storage
strategy and that might be you need you
might need a node above all your micro
fulfillment that is you know your
traditional Warehouse where you are
storing stuff because you what maybe
here's the question what's the ideal
inventory number of inventory turns in a
micro fulfillment according to your
Corey I I love that question and and
it's you know what our technology is
built around I mean we try to have less
than eight weeks of inventory on hand at
every given you know every given turn so
you know
what's the math on that right like it
it's it's not 12 right but it's more
than six yeah it's about six yeah yeah
you know and it depends on the category
we have some that are six we have some
that are eight you know so it's all
about creating turns but you also at
this stage in micro fulfillment in my
opinion the the lead time in the moqs
inbound from Brands themselves is
equally as important as that
conversation and there there's a mix to
that right and it you know
for us having six buildings solving a
one to two day problem versus 300
buildings you know solving a 15-minute
problem it's a lot easier of a problem
to have exactly and I mean if you if you
go from a sixth turn to let's say three
turn right
it's not just the turn that's the
problem now you got dead inventory
inside the building that from uh it that
inventory will not be profitable anymore
because you're already in an expensive
real estate market right like
specifically speaking or
you know I've seen micro fulfillment
centers that have you know 12 feet
ceilings like that's again you don't
have air storage right like so you're
paying the same square footage you don't
have you know pallet tracks that you can
store on or have you know strategies
where you could optimally utilize the
cube that's available to you I think
micro fulfillment is amazing but finding
a good partner and not just going by
yourself trying to do this I think
that's that would be the recommendation
to almost anyone that's looking to you
get closer to the customer
you know it might feel easier but I
don't think it is and and at some point
that's where robotics comes in right
there's no question like building
density and throughput out of the same
cube is a critical thing and there's
automation partners that can do that
shuttle systems are really expensive to
go put in but you know you're getting a
lot of density out of that you know is
your throughput relative is that you
know unit economics going to be in in
the black on that one I don't know you
know I think that there's
you can have an asrs or a shuttle system
Corey but if you don't have control over
how your inventory turns and you got
dead inventory your cube in is not equal
to your cube out you got a huge problem
and that's gonna catch up to you in less
than six months and that's why it's so
critical to understand your assortment
because it worked backwards from that
and if you can create more turns from
the same set of inventories you can you
can create faster turns and get stuff to
the consumers in a more profitable way
with all of these things and it starts
with merchandising in my opinion because
it works backwards and where you place
inventory and how you place it
absolutely
can't say that enough no makes all the
sense and you know quarries were getting
to the end I I could think of like 30
more things I want to talk to you about
if we get up on time I mean it's getting
there buddy it went super super fast but
I I do want to you know Corey if
if this conversation has sparked
interest for somebody who has been
thinking about micro fulfillment and and
you know it was has heard this
this uh podcast session are there any
kind of lesson learns or like any any
advice you would give to someone who's
just thinking about it and what what are
you know some some pieces of advice you
would give them as they're on that
Journey
I would say uh the data is critical and
listen to the data uh don't try to bite
off more than you can chew but listen to
the data and the most important thing
that you need to measure as a brand
um is the percent of of Revenue compared
to your total operation and and I think
you need to look at your inventory
control of where it's placed and try not
to
separate your inventories for different
programs in different locations and try
to have as much inventory control from
similar locations because that's a
really
fast way to lose control is by doing
that if you put your Shopify inventory
in this 3pl and your Amazon bulk
business and this distributor and this
inventory you know for Walmart
marketplace and that 3pl because they're
on the east coast and now you have the
whole country covered but you have three
different you know programs with the
same inventory sets being managed that's
a recipe for disaster and I see so much
of that still yep
great advice great advice I appreciate
that buddy
well listen I want to give you the
opportunity to share with everyone
um where they could go to follow you you
know maybe where you spend some time on
what social platforms you're on and uh
and the best way to learn more about
DaVinci micro fulfillment yeah thank you
uh LinkedIn of course you can certainly
reach out to me on LinkedIn I make it a
point to respond to all the messages
there you can follow our LinkedIn page
as well DaVinci microfulfillment.com or
DaVinci mfc.com there's a contact us
form or you can reach out to me
c-o-r-e-y-a at DaVinci mfc.com I will
gladly respond
amazing amazing thank you Corey an
absolute pleasure having you on the show
today uh the pleasure was mine I really
appreciate it thank you
hi I'm ninada charya CEO and co-founder
of fulfillment IQ and I'm here with Dan
Cole cro and partner at fulfillment IQ
we're the team behind the Ecom Logistics
podcast our mission is to provide you
with genuine insights from our work
alongside Logistics leaders to help you
improve your supply chain in the Ecom
Logistics podcast we share the knowledge
and the insights we've gained from
working alongside amazing Brands
retailers 3pls nvcs so you can make the
most out of your supply chain Journey if
you like what you're hearing we truly
appreciate your support with the five
star rating on your favorite podcasting
Channel your feedback not only keeps us
going but also helps others find the
podcast if you think fulfillment IQ can
assist you or if you have an idea
related to Logistics just reach out to
me on LinkedIn I'm always up for a chat
and ready to explore new possibilities
together stay tuned to the Ecom
Logistics podcast on your favorite
podcast platform for fresh and practical
insights into Ecom Logistics until next
time let's keep making a difference in
logistics together